Tobias Witter

Humboldt-University of Berlin,

Office: Unter den Linden 6, 10099 Berlin, Germany

Phone: +4930 2093 99450

Email: tobias.witter@wiwi.hu-berlin.de

Webpage: tobias-witter.com



Oct 2017 - present

Education

Humboldt-University of Berlin, Germany

Berlin Doctoral Program of Economics and Management Science (BDPEMS)

- PhD Student in Accounting, Supervisor: Joachim Gassen
- Average Grade: 2.0 (equivalent to A-)
- Coursework completed: Econometric Methods, Advanced Econometrics, Advanced Microeconomic Theory, Advanced Microeconomic Analysis, Management Science I & II, Advanced Financial Economics, Experimental Research, Advanced Topics in Quantitative Empirical Accounting Research, Financial Accounting Research Group

Beuth University of Applied Sciences, Berlin, Germany

Master of Arts in Management and Consulting

• Final Grade: excellent (1.1, equivalent to "A"), graduated with honors & top of class

Management School Gustave Eiffel at University Paris-Est Créteil, Paris, France

Erasmus Program Exchange Student in Master's Program International Business Management

• Final Grade: excellent (1.0, equivalent to "A")

Federal University of Applied Administrative Sciences, Berlin, Germany

Bachelor of Arts in Public Management

• Final Grade: excellent (1.5, equivalent to "A"), graduated top of class

Oct 2010 - Sep 2013

Oct 2013 - Oct 2015

Sep 2014 – Jan 2015

Professional experience

Institute of Accounting and Auditing at Humboldt-University of Berlin, Germany

Oct 2017 – present

- Research Assistant
- Teaching: Managerial Accounting (Winter 2017 & Winter 2018), Valuation (Summer 2017), Undergraduate Course Empirical Accounting Research (Winter 2018), Accounting Theory and Earnings Management (Summer 2019)

Beuth University of Applied Sciences, Berlin, Germany

Oct 2016 - Sep 2017

- Lecturer (Freelance)
- Team of Matthias Schmidt (Professor of Business Management and Business Ethics)
- Taught an introductory course in management and human resources management

German Statutory Pension Insurance Scheme, Berlin, Germany Department for France, Italy, Tunisia, Morocco, and Algeria

Oct 2013 - Sep 2017

- Advisor and caseworker, Working language: German, English, French
- Advice for cross-border pension regulations
 Frequent advisory activities in France, e.g. Paris, Marseille, Strasbourg
- Processing of insurance and pension applications

German Statutory Pension Insurance Scheme, Berlin, Germany Internships in four departments

Jan 2010 - Apr 2013

- Controlling & Risk Management
- International Office & Advisory
- Strategic Planning & Quality Management
- Insurance & Pension Payments

Compulsory Paid Community Service

Jul 2009 - Mar 2010

Honors & Volunteer Experience

Berlin Doctoral Program of Economics and Management Science (BDPEMS) Elected Student Representative	Feb 2018 – present
Beuth University English Language Competition Award for the 2 nd Place for an English essay on the impact of digitalization on society	Oct 2014
Buddy-Program of the Beuth University of Applied Sciences Study Buddy for a French exchange student (administrative and study matters)	Mar 2014 – Aug 2014
Federal University of Applied Administrative Sciences, Berlin, Germany	Feb 2012 – Sep 2013

Elected Student Representative,

Student Member of University Senate & Student Member of Faculty Council

Research

Research statement

My research interest centers around the intersection of financial and managerial accounting. Broadly, I am interested in the preferences managers have and how their preferences lead to choices that are ultimately reflected in their actions and disclosures. I plan to focus my PhD thesis on how information variation is captured in managerial actions, e.g. how uncertain information lead to changes of government agencies' actions and how that affects firm behavior.

Work in Progress

Budgetary uncertainty: Does it have a disciplinary effect?

Research idea, first presented in Brown Bag Seminar in Jan 2019

Offenlegungsverhalten von Emittenten nach dem Vermögensanlagengesetz

(Topic: Disclosure behavior of firms in the German gray capital market) together with Joachim Gassen

Articles in Journals

Habitus und Mimesis: Neue Ansätze für das Change Management aus der Theorie Pierre Bourdieus,
 OrganisationsEntwicklung, 2/2017, pp. 104-106. (without peer-review)

(Topic: Discussion of a change management approach using the concept of Pierre Bourdieus theory) together with Jürgen Materne (Professor for Business Administration)

Computing & Language Skills

Software Packages & Related Skills

R, GitHub, STATA, LaTeX, Mathematica, Python

Language Skills

German (Native), English (Fluent), French (Fluent)

Hobbies & Interests

Scuba Diving, Running, Swimming, Political & historical literature